[SPEAKER_00]: Bhante, I've noticed that when I concentrate on something for an extended period, it brings about a sense of bliss and peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: These states stick around and help me deal with life's challenges.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wonder if continuing this concentration practice might lead me to a point where I become untroubled by external things forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is this the right path and how long might it take?
[SPEAKER_00]: I've invested a fair bit of time and I want to make sure that it's worthwhile.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would probably need a bit more details, but it doesn't sound like the right path.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if concentration helps you deal with the life challenges, sounds more like management practice to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead, you should ask yourself why you challenged in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do you need concentration to help you deal with the challenges?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were not challenged to begin with, you don't need to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to concentrate.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are unmoved to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the direction of practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: If concentration helps you cope, because you just can't bear it, fine, but don't confuse that for the practice of the dhamma, because it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't arise... it will not arise... it will not result in understanding, because you're... you're going the wrong way about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're going... trying to manage the suffering, which is kind of what putujanas do, because they don't know the escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for as long as you don't abandon the value of suffering management,
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not look for the way of uprooting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to, basically, leave yourself no way out, in order to seek the true escape from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: To see the real cause.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, if you stop managing your suffering, if you recognize that you're surrounded by it, like the king surrounded by the armies from the four directions,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you realize, okay, the weight of the problem, and then you can be able to look for it, for the way out rightly, through uprooting the craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exemplified with what I just said.
[SPEAKER_01]: You ask yourself, why am I bothered in the first place?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is life challenging me?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why can life challenge me in the first place?
[SPEAKER_01]: Rather than, oh, I found something that helps me always deal with different challenges.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I want to be not challenged to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why am I challenged?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why am I challenged to begin with?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the dhamma does not provide instruction how to deal with the life challenges.
[SPEAKER_01]: The dhamma uproots the life, so there are no challenges for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're at ease.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, I guess, what I got from this question was like, if you... if he keeps on concentrating and focusing and doing this for peace, it will... it will build up, build up, build up, and these whole waking moments... Will just culminate on its own, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, that's... that's not how it works, which is exactly why I started describing this as two opposite directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot be managing your suffering and at the same time trying to uproot it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because in order to uproot it, you need to stop giving in to the tendency and craving for management.
[SPEAKER_01]: Management is a quick fix.
[SPEAKER_01]: Management is de-pressuring of the container.
[SPEAKER_01]: An uprooting can occur if the container is pressurized rightly to the right extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, each time you give in to a management, you release the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's mutually exclusive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Releasing the pressure, building the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to give up that tendency towards management, in order for that pressure that's been built up to turn you in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: See the cause for the liability to be bothered.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is unwholesome behavior by body, speech and mind that's still perpetuated, lack of establishment in virtue, lack of sense restraint, lack of knowledge and transparency in regard to your intentions, lack of enduring the hindrances on the right level, without acting out of them, without trying to get rid... lack of development.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, concentration basically provides you this like a narrow focusing, thinning out, where you stop seeing the problem, while it's still very much in front of your face.